Guide to the Franklin Furnace Ephemera Collection, Compiled by Matthew Hogan MSS.206
Fales Library and Special Collections
Franklin Furnace Ephemera Collection, Compiled by Matthew Hogan
1970-2014
Fales Library and Special Collections
Franklin Furnace (Archive)
Hogan, Matthew
MSS.206
106.25 Linear Feet in 102 record cartons, 8 manuscript boxes, 2 oversized flat boxes
Since its inception in 1976, Franklin Furnace Archive, Inc. has been devoted to documenting and preserving ephemeral art forms. The Franklin Furnace Ephemera Collection contains invitations, flyers, postcards, and advertisements collected by Franklin Furnace. The collection is international in scope, comprising materials in numerous languages related to art events in numerous countries. Materials date from 1970 to 2014.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by the Franklin Furnace Archive, 2007. The accession number associated with this gift is 2007.206. Additional donations were made in 2009-2020. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are 2009.2067, 2011.206, 2013.206, 2014.206, and 2020.009.
Arrangement
Materials in the Franklin Furnace Ephemera Collection are arranged alphabetically by venue. Fales archivists have operated under a processing scheme which retains a broad definition of the term "venue," used to refer to the entity that is primarily responsible for a given event or work. In this way not only are museums, galleries, nightclubs and performance spaces classified as venues, but collectives, institutions and individual artists as well. For each box, the alphabet range and a short list of any notable venues are given in the finding aid; the full list of venues is available, please contact Fales Library staff (fales.library@nyu.edu) to see the list.
Note on alphabetization: In instances where a proper name is the first part of a corporate name, the venue has been arranged based on the first letter of the first name (e.g. "Leo Castelli Gallery" has been placed under "L" for Leo). Wherever an individual has been identified as a venue, the first letter of the last name takes priority (e.g. "Tehching Hsieh" has been placed under "H" for Hsieh).
Materials added to the collection in 2018 and 2020 do not follow the original arrangement scheme. Materials that were pre-sorted by venue name are listed as "Unarranged" after the alphabetical list of venues. Materials that were not pre-sorted have been listed at the end as "Unalphabetized". These materials have not been arranged by an archivist, and are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Historical Note
Franklin Furnace Archive, Inc.> is an organization whose mission is to present, preserve, interpret, proselytize and advocate on behalf of avant-garde art, especially forms that may be vulnerable due to institutional neglect, their ephemeral nature, or politically unpopular content. The Archive was founded by Martha Wilson in New York City in 1976; since then, Franklin Furnace has been one of the strongest driving forces behind the documentation and preservation of ephemeral and avant-garde art forms.
Related Materials at Fales
Downtown Flyers and Invitations Collection (MSS.119)
A.I.R. Gallery Archives (MSS.184)
Collective: Unconscious Archive (MSS.225)
Creative Time Archive (MSS.179)
Fashion Moda Archive (MSS.091)
Judson Memorial Church Archive
REPOHistory Archive (MSS.094)
Ubu Repertory Theater Script Collection (MSS.120)
Martha Wilson Papers (MSS.175)
Scope and Contents
The Franklin Furnace Ephemera Collection contains fliers, invitations, promotional objects and other printed ephemera related to events hosted at more than 9000 international venues. The contents of the collection are the result of a massive collection process undertaken by Matthew Hogan, a Franklin Furnace archivist. The venues documented in the collection span the globe, with particular strengths in New York and California. Materials are in several languages, including English, Spanish, Dutch, German, Italian and French. Specific strengths include performance spaces like Highways Performance Space and St. Mark's Church-in-the-Bowery, as well as nightclubs such as the Limelight, Tunnel and Palladium. Materials date from 1970 to 2014.
Alternative spaces (Arts facilities) -- New York (State) -- New York.; Artists.; Art, Modern -- 20th century -- Exhibitions.; Art, Modern -- 21st century -- Exhibitions.; Franklin Furnace (Archive); ABC No Rio (New York, N.Y.); 92nd Street Y (New York, N.Y.); 80 Washington Square East Galleries; 55 Mercer St. Gallery; Centre for Contemporary Canadian Art (New York, N.Y.). 49th Parallel (Art gallery). 49th Parallel (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Museum; Center for Book Arts (New York, N.Y.); Collective for Living Cinema (New York, N.Y.); Creative Time, Inc.; Dance Theater Workshop; Deitch Projects; Dia Center for the Arts (New York, N.Y.); Dieu Donné Papermill; Drawing Center (New York, N.Y.); Group Material (Firm: New York, N.Y.); Gracie Mansion Gallery; Grey Art Gallery & Study Center; Gay Men's Health Crisis, Inc.; Getty Research Institute for the History of Art and the Humanities; Film Forum, inc.; Gagosian Gallery; Bronx Museum of the Arts; Brooklyn Academy of Music; Art in General, Inc.; Barbara Gladstone Gallery; Andy Warhol Museum; Anthology Film Archives; Robert Miller Gallery (New York, N.Y.); St. Mark's Church In-the-Bowery (New York, N.Y.). Poetry Project; St. Mark's Church In-the-Bowery (New York, N.Y.); San Francisco Museum of Modern Art; Performance Space 122; Public Art Fund (New York, N.Y.); Queens Museum of Art; REPOhistory (Organization); Storefront Gallery for Art and Architecture; Thread Waxing Space (Gallery); Tony Shafrazi Gallery; Tunnel (Nightclub); School of Visual Arts (New York, N.Y.); Sculpture Center (New York, N.Y.); Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum; SoundArt Foundation; Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.); Museum of Contemporary Art (Los Angeles, Calif.); New York Public Library; New Museum of Contemporary Art (New York, N.Y.); MIX NYC; Millennium Film Workshop; Museum of the City of New York; Museo del Barrio (New York, N.Y.); P.P.O.W. (Gallery); Pat Hearn Gallery; P.S. 1 Contemporary Art Center; Printed Matter, Inc.; Pace Gallery; Nuyorican Poets Cafe; Paper Tiger Television Collective (Firm); Palladium (Nightclub); Lower East Side Printshop, Inc.; Lower Manhattan Cultural Council; Highways Performance Space; Henry Street Settlement (New York, N.Y.); Institute of Contemporary Arts (London, England); Institute for Art and Urban Resources; Joyce SoHo (New York, N.Y.); International Center of Photography; Metropolitan Museum of Art (New York, N.Y.); Midtown Y Photography Gallery (New York, N.Y.); Mattress Factory; Merce Cunningham Dance Company; Marian Goodman Gallery; Matthew Marks Gallery; Madison Art Center; Manhattan Neighborhood Network; Long Beach Museum of Art; Los Angeles Contemporary Exhibitions (Gallery); Los Angeles County Museum of Art; Whitney Museum of American Art; Fashion Moda (Group); Exit Art (Gallery: New York, N.Y.); Estate Project for Artists with AIDS; Judson Memorial Church (New York, N.Y.); Kitchen Center for Video, Music, Dance, Performance, Film, and Literature (New York, N.Y.); Knitting Factory (Nightclub); La Mama Experimental Theatre Club; Lannan Foundation; Leo Castelli Gallery; Limelight (Nightclub); Lincoln Center for the Performing Arts; Visual AIDS (Organization); Walker Art Center; Ubu Gallery; Ubu Repertory Theater; Ward-Nasse Gallery; White Columns (Gallery); A.I.R. Gallery (New York, N.Y.); Amos Eno Gallery
- 00 - 80 M (Box 1)
  General
  Notable venues include 49th Parallel, 4th Street Photo Gallery and 55 Mercer Gallery.
- 80 W - Ahs (Box 2)
  Notable venues include 80 Washington Square East Galleries, the 92nd Street Y, and ABC No Rio.
- Ai - American Ar (Box 3)
  Notable venues include A.I.R. Gallery.
- American Art - Andre (Box 4)
  Notable venues include Amos Eno Gallery.
- Andrea- Ariz (Box 5)
  Notable venues include the Andy Warhol Museum and Anthology Film Archives.
- Arizo - Art L (Box 6)
  Notable venues include Art in General.
- Art M - Artists S (Box 7)
  Notable venues include Artists Against AIDS.
- Artists T- Asp (Box 8)
- Ass - Baq (Box 9)
  Notable venues include Bang on a Can.
- Bar - Bell (Box 10)
  Notable venues include Barbara Gladstone Gallery and Barnsdall Art Park.
- Belm - Blue (Box 11)
- Blum - Bronwy (Box 12)
  Notable venues include Bowery Poetry Club.
- Bronx - Brooklyn L (Box 13)
  Notable venues inclue Bronx Museum of the Arts and Brooklyn Academy of Music.
- Brooklyn M - California M (Box 14)
  Notable venues include Brooklyn Museum.
- California Mu - Caste (Box 15)
- Castel - Centraal (Box 16)
  Notable venues include Center for Book Arts.
- Central - CID (Box 17)
- Cies - Colleg (Box 18)
  Notable venues include Collective for Living Cinema and Collective: Unconscious.
- College - Cooper T (Box 19)
- Cooper U - Cz (Box 20)
  Notable venues include Creative Time and Cubiculo.
- D - Dance Theater Workshop (Box 21)
  Notable venues include Dance Theater Workshop.
- Dance Theater Workshop - Ded (Box 22)
  Notable venus include Dance Theater Workshop and Danceteria.
- Dee - Dik (Box 23)
  Notable venues include Deitch Projects, Dia Art Foundation/Center for the Arts, and Dieu Donne Papermill.
- Dil - Dq (Box 24)
  Notable venues include Dixon Place.
- Dr - Eif (Box 25)
  Notable venues include the Drawing Center.
- Eig - Ev (Box 26)
  Notable venues include Estate Project for Artists with AIDS.
- Eva - Fers (Box 27)
  Notable venues include Exit Art and Fashion Moda.
- Fes - Fond (Box 28)
  Notable venues include Fez and Film Forum.
- Foo - Fris (Box 29)
  Notable venues include Franklin Furnace Archive Inc.
- Frit - Galerie Meh (Box 30)
  Notable venues include Gagosian Gallery.
- Galerie Mei - Gallery K (Box 31)
- Gallery L - God (Box 32)
  Notable venues include Gay Men's Health Crisis and Getty Research Institute.
  Note: All venues associated with "the Getty" (Getty Center, J. Paul Getty Trust, Getty Museum) have been collocated under "Getty Research Institute."
- Goe - Gret (Box 33)
  Notable venues include Gracie Mansion Gallery.
- Grey - Harp (Box 34)
  Notable venues include Grey Art Gallery and Group Material.
- Harr - High (Box 35)
  Notable venues include Henry Street Settlement.
- Highw - Howd (Box 36)
  Notable venues include Highways Performance Space.
- Howe - Institute of Contemporary Art (Box 37)
  Notable venues include Institute for Art and Urban Resources.
- Institute of Contemporary Arts - Irvine (Box 38)
  Notable venues include Institute of Contemporary Arts, London, and International Center of Photography.
- Irving - Jig (Box 39)
- Jil - June (Box 40)
  Notable venues include Joyce Theater and Judson Memorial Church.
- Jung - Kluwer (Box 41)
  Notable venues include the Kitchen.
- Kn - La Mama (Box 42)
  Notable venues include Knitting Factory and La Mama E.T.C.
- La N - Letz (Box 43)
  Notable venues include Lannan Foundation and Leo Castelli Gallery.
- Lev - Lod (Box 44)
  Notable venues include Limelight and Lincoln Center.
- Loe - Los Angeles H (Box 45)
  Notable venues include Long Beach Museum of Art, Los Angeles Contemporary Exhibitions and Los Angeles County Museum of Art.
- Los Angeles I - Madison Art Center (Box 46)
  Notable venues include Lower East Side Printshop, Lower Manhattan Cultural Council, and Madison Art Center.
- Madison Art Center - Mary C (Box 47)
  Notable venues include Madison Art Center, Manhattan Neighborhood Network and Marian Goodman Gallery.
- Mary D - Merk (Box 48)
  Notable venues include Matthew Marks Gallery, Mattress Factory and Merce Cunningham Studio.
- Merl - Minner (Box 49)
  Notable venues include Metropolitan Museum of Art, Midtown Y Photography Gallery and Millennium Film Workshop.
- Minnes - Multi (Box 50)
  Notable venues include MIX Film Festival.
- Multia - Museum of Contemporary Art, San Diego (Box 51)
  Notable venues include Museo del Barrio, Museum of the City of New York and Museum of Contemporary Art, Los Angeles.
- Museum of Contemporary Art, San Diego - Nas (Box 52)
  Notable venues include Museum of Modern Art.
- Nass - New Di (Box 53)
- New Dir - New York G (Box 54)
  Notable venues include New Museum.
- New York Ga - Nex (Box 55)
  Notable venues include New York Public Library.
- Next - Oi (Box 56)
  Notable venues include Nuyorican Poets' Cafe.
- Oil - Pacific N (Box 57)
  Notable venues include Pace Gallery.
- Pacific No - Ped (Box 58)
  Notable venues include Palladium, Paper Tiger Television and Pat Hearn Gallery.
- Pedr - Pland (Box 59)
- Plane - Printed Matter, Inc. (Box 60)
  Notable venues include P.P.O.W. Gallery and Printed Matter, Inc.
- Printed Matter, Inc. - Public Aq (Box 61)
  Notable venues include Printed Matter, Inc., P.S. 1 Museum/Institute for Contemporary Art, and P.S. 122.
- Public Ar - Randol (Box 62)
  Notable venues include Public Art Fund, Public Theater and Queens Museum of Art.
- Random - Ricj (Box 63)
  Notable venues include REPOHistory.
- Rick - Rouk (Box 64)
  Notable venues include Robert Miller Gallery and Ronald Feldman Fine Arts.
- Roul - Saint Mark's Church-in-the-Bowery, Danspace Project (Box 65)
- Saint Mark's Church-in-the-Bowery, Danspace Project - San Francisco Az (Box 66)
  Notable venues include Saint Mark's Church-in-the-Bowery - Danspace Project, Ontological-Hysteric Theater, and Poetry Project.
- San Francisco B - Saras (Box 67)
  Notable venues include San Francisco Museum of Modern Art.
- Sarat - Send (Box 68)
  Notable venues include School of Visual Arts and Sculpture Center.
- Sene - Sm (Box 69)
- Sma - Sonn (Box 70)
  Notable venues include Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum.
- Sono - Stac (Box 71)
  Notable venues include SoundArt Foundation.
- Stad - Studit (Box 72)
  Notable venues include Storefront for Art and Architecture.
- Studiu - Tav (Box 73)
- Tave - Toby (Box 74)
  Notable venues include Thread Waxing Space.
- Toc - Tun (Box 75)
  Notable venues include Tony Shafrazi Gallery.
- Tunc - University In (Box 76)
  Notable venues include Tunnel, Ubu Gallery and Ubu Repertory Theater.
- University Io - Vie (Box 77)
- Viej - Walj (Box 78)
  Notable venues include Visual AIDS.
- Walk - Westbr (Box 79)
  Notable venues include Walker Art Center and Ward-Nasse Gallery.
- Westbro - Williamq (Box 80)
  Notable venues include White Columns and Whitney Museum of American Art.
- Williamr - World L (Box 81)
- World M - Z (Box 82)
- Unarranged A (Box 95, Folder 1-8)
- Unarranged B (Box 95, Folder 9-13)
- Unarranged C (Box 95, Folder 14-22)
- Unarranged D (Box 95, Folder 23-25, Box 96, Folder 1)
- Unarranged E (Box 96, Folder 2-4)
- Unarranged F (Box 96, Folder 5-6)
- Unarranged G (Box 96, Folder 7-8)
- Unarranged H (Box 96, Folder 9-11)
- Unarranged I (Box 96, Folder 12)
- Unarranged J (Box 96, Folder 13)
- Unarranged K (Box 96, Folder 14)
- Unarranged L (Box 96, Folder 15-19)
- Unarranged M (Box 96, Folder 20-24)
- Unarranged N (Box 96, Folder 25-30)
- Unarranged O (Box 96, Folder 31)
- Unarranged P (Box 97, Folder 1-5)
- Unarranged Q (Box 97, Folder 6)
- Unarranged R (Box 97, Folder 7)
- Unarranged S (Box 97, Folder 8-14)
- Unarranged T (Box 97, Folder 15-18)
- Unarranged U (Box 97, Folder 19)
- Unarranged V (Box 97, Folder 20)
- Unarranged W (Box 97, Folder 21-22)
- Unarranged Y (Box 97, Folder 23)
- Unarranged Z (Box 97, Folder 24-25)
- Unalphabetized (Box 97, Folder 26-30)
- Unalphabetized (Box 98, Folder 1-28)
- Unalphabetized (Box 99, Folder 1-29)
- Unalphabetized (Box 100, Folder 1-29)
- Unalphabetized (Box 101, Folder 1-8)
- Unalphabetized (Box 102, Folder 1-5)
- Unalphabetized (Flat-file-folder 2)
- Unalphabetized, 2005-2006 (Box 103, Folder 1-10)
- Unalphabetized, 2005-2006 (Box 104, Folder 1-9)
- Unalphabetized, 2005-2006 (Box 105, Folder 1-10)
- Unalphabetized, 2005-2006 (Box 106, Folder 1-9)
- Unalphabetized, 2005-2006 (Box 107, Folder 1-9)